<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="kujua.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="kujua.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-02-05T20:07:14+01:00</updated><id>kujua.github.io/</id><subtitle>Technology Blog by Wolfgang Loder. Software development technologies and methods covered amongst others: Elixir, Elm. .NET, C#, Functional Programming, Machine Learning
</subtitle><entry><title>Self-Publishing vs Traditional Publishing</title><link href="kujua.github.io/2016/09/03/self-publishing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self-Publishing vs Traditional Publishing" /><published>2016-09-03T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-09-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>kujua.github.io/2016/09/03/self-publishing</id><content type="html" xml:base="kujua.github.io/2016/09/03/self-publishing.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My experiences with self-publishing a book and a traditional publisher. It is not always as it appears at first sight.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mid August 2016 I published my book &lt;em&gt;Erlang and Elixir for Imperative Programmers&lt;/em&gt;. I have written about the experience in &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/09/01/book-leanpub-scrivener.html&quot;&gt;another blog entry&lt;/a&gt;. About a week after publishing the finished book, a traditional publisher whose name shall not be revealed approached me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the first feeling of being flattered by such an approach, I started negotiating the contract. The first draft of the contract let me cringe. Perhaps to explain my experience with contracts: I was freelancer and self-employed the last 20+ years and did on-premises software projects in two continents and several countries, all with their own little differences in contract laws. Therefore I am very aware of many pitfalls in contracts, and the publisher’s contract was so vaguely worded that anything could be interpreted in. One clause - the &lt;em&gt;non-competition&lt;/em&gt; clause - was standing out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“During the term of this Agreement, You agree to not publish or furnish to any other publisher any Work that is on the exact same subject and that targets the exact same market and that could hurt sales of the Work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Work&lt;/em&gt; in this case means my book. Exceptions from this clause are articles or anything published before the agreement was signed. Other clauses in the contract were similar vague and I got the feeling they were done in that way to lock an author in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few rounds of negotiation I rejected the offer, but that was also based on the fact that they could not meet my ideas of publishing technical books:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My thinking is that we can’t publish technical books like fiction books, because there is more to such a book than just text. The underlying languages, frameworks, programs etc. are changing regularly. Having long editorial phases before printing a book makes the book’s contents outdated from the start. A friend of mine had written a book for a publisher about a database he himself developed together with a friend. It took the publisher almost two years to bring this book into the catalog and on Safari for online reading. Needless to say it was not a success.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The community should be integrated into the decision about the contents of the book. This was not done a lot with my &lt;em&gt;Erlang/Elixir&lt;/em&gt; book, but I plan to do this much more with future books. It is an approach similar to open source projects where features are proposed. Participants can vote for or against feature requests and make sure they as readers or potential readers get the book they are looking for.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not everyone needs a printed book, but rather an ebook that is often updated. I plan updates for the published Erlang/Elixir book at least every 6-8 weeks for a year and want to do the same for future books once finished. There will be on-demand printed books, but the content of the printed book is a bit different from the ebook. The ebook is up-to-date the moment it is bought or downloaded, the printed book is a snapshot at certain milestones. The printed book also has a slightly different content being black and white, so images like diagrams are b/w and code is not highlighted. The text as such is not different. The reason lies in the high costs of color prints: a b/w book can be sold for 15-20 USD, a color book would cost at least 35 USD.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A technical book is not only a book, there is at least code accompanying it, but there may be other goodies as well like videos, templates etc. depending on the book’s subject. Readers have to get access to it in a way that protects the author’s rights and also gives the readers the feeling to have bought something useful they would not get elsewhere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is no surprise that the traditional publisher sent me this statement after I was trying to discuss the above mentioned points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I do not think we can be as nimble as you need us to be with regards to updating the eBook often.  Also, we cannot make the changes to the contract as you’re requesting. “&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me it is a clear decision: go with a traditional publisher, get potentially locked into a contract and be on the backfoot regarding updated content from the start. I strongly believe that - at least with technical books - traditional publishers will have a hard time competing against self-publishing authors. To be a real competion, self-publishing needs to sort out the following, though:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Editing, both language and content. Authors like me who are not English native speakers may come up with “awkward phrases” or grammatically incorrect sentences. I have worked in English speaking countries for 15 years, but I know that I will never reach a proficiency in English as with my native German. A native speaker needs to go through the book and sort out everything that is incorrect or sounds odd. Similar applies to the contents of a book. Having worked for decades as software developer does not mean that I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; everything. Readers of a book expect to gain knowledge and not having to question every statement. Technical reviews are the only way to get the contents right.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Formatting. Content is certainly important, but it also needs to be presented in a nice and appealing way. I have seen this with my first book when I did not always find the right proportion between code listings and text. Results are gaps that interrupt the reading flow. Again, this can be sorted out, but we authors need to put more effort into formatting or let it do somebody else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional publishers will do editing, formatting and proof reading. On the other side, they will also influence the contents as they see fit with the author having no real control over it once a contract is signed. If the “additional exposure” is more worth than the vastly reduced royalties is a question authors must answer for themselves. Self-publishing also means self-marketing and not everyone is happy with that. I have seen that being present in social media all the time and pitching my own book is necessary to get readers. Stopping for a few days also stops sales. If someone does not like that, self-publishing is not the right approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have made up my mind and will continue self-publishing. Learning from the writing process of my first book I will sort out the editing and formatting problems and will also engage readers and potential readers more. I hope it will be successful and bring the quality of self-publishing technical books forward.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>My experiences with self-publishing a book and a traditional publisher. It is not always as it appears at first sight.</summary></entry><entry><title>Publishing a book on Leanpub</title><link href="kujua.github.io/2016/09/01/book-leanpub-scrivener.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Publishing a book on Leanpub" /><published>2016-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>kujua.github.io/2016/09/01/book-leanpub-scrivener</id><content type="html" xml:base="kujua.github.io/2016/09/01/book-leanpub-scrivener.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A few days ago I published my first book on Leanpub. Overall, it was a very good experience with no major problems.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://leanpub.com&quot;&gt;Leanpub&lt;/a&gt; is a self-publishing platform that encourages &lt;em&gt;lean&lt;/em&gt; publishing: Even if the book is not finished it should be made available to potential readers and buyers. It is like a kickstarter book project where readers support the writing of a book, not knowing if they will ever get a finished product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a good idea to publish the book in its infant state, but there are pitfalls as well. I published the first chapters of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://leanpub.com/erlangandelixirforimperativeprogrammers&quot;&gt;Erlang/Elixir book&lt;/a&gt; and then it stayed there for a long time, because I was contracted for an unexpected project and could not write. Fortunately the readers I had at that time did not demand their money back. It was a bit embarassing for me - all the time estimations I had were completely blown away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estimations were also wrong, because unexpected issues can occur:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Code highlighting was not always working. I have to stress that this issue also had to do with misunderstandings how the highlighting engine works. In any case, whenever I went to Leanpub’s Google group my issues were answered within the delays of dfferent time zones and support was very helpful.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Formatting with markdown did not always bring the expected result. I remember trying to define a table and wasted a whole day making this work. It is this sort of problem where you have something working, then you add a feature like in this case a row or column and it totally falls apart. Eventually I gave up and formatted it in a different way, because &lt;em&gt;epub&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;mobi&lt;/em&gt; would not render the table as I wanted anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I had to work out my writing process and it took me a while until I was happy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once everything was in place and my external project had finished writing the book was moving on a fair pace. The most important thing that can be said about Leanpub is that it never got into my way. When I wanted to create the book to preview it is was just doing it without any problems. I used Dropbox publishing, so my texts were copied to the shared folder and the results were loaded to this folder as well where I could download it from. There were a few times when the website was not available, but I guess this had to do with the different time zones and nightly maintenance on the Leanpub servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s examine my writing process a little bit more:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As mentioned before, all file exchange between my computer and Leanpub was done via a Dropbox shared folder.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I did not want to work on the Dropbox folder, so I created a project on my computer as working folder.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being a software developer, I set up a git project to make sure I have versions of my files and pushed the local repository to a private GitHub repository.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I also did not want to work directly on the markup files that are used to create the book. The reason again is to keep files I work on separated from the files I created a book from, even if it is a preview only. Both sets of files are in the git repository and if something goes wrong - and it will! - it is possible to go back to a previous version.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All this sounds a bit complicated, but I never lost anything I have written. It needs a fair amount of copying text, though. This can be achieved by doing it manually or automating it. I wrote some scripts for automation, but most of the time I just copied changed text around, especially at a later stage of the book. Sometimes it is good not to trust your own programming abilities 100%…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is not only text that had to be copied, but also images and code examples. One of the challenges was to keep the running number of the code examples correct. The examples are numbered like &lt;em&gt;Example 4-2&lt;/em&gt; which means example number two in chapter 4. First, I went through the chapters and did the numbering manually, but when the chapters got larger and the changes more, I just wrote a small Perl script to automate this task.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A very important, but also a bit boring task is proof reading before it can be given to somebody else for editing. Reading through 300 pages again and again is not very pleasant and takes some time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote the book on a MacBook Pro with lots of memory to have all applications I need opened including one or two virtual machines. My editor for the text is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.literatureandlatte.com/scrivener.php&quot;&gt;Scrivener&lt;/a&gt; - I used it for some time now and it deserves its own blog post. For the code I used different editors, but mostly &lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io/&quot;&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leanpub also provides a PDF version that can be uploaded to Amazon for offering a print-on-demand book. In fact, they encourage authors to do this once the book is 100% finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a very good experience for me to publish on Leanpub. They don’t take a lot of money, so there is a nice chunk of royalties left. I can only recommend it to anyone who wants to publish a book.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>A few days ago I published my first book on Leanpub. Overall, it was a very good experience with no major problems.</summary></entry><entry><title>Software Engineering Series</title><link href="kujua.github.io/2016/08/02/about-software-engineering-series.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Software Engineering Series" /><published>2016-08-02T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>kujua.github.io/2016/08/02/about-software-engineering-series</id><content type="html" xml:base="kujua.github.io/2016/08/02/about-software-engineering-series.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;software-engineering-series&quot;&gt;Software Engineering Series&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This series of books will describe topics in software engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each book has one topic and will go as deep into it as possible in about 100 pages. It should be an interesting read for a weekend. After finishing the book the reader should have a good understanding of the topic in hand and can then go into more details with the help of the resource listing the book provides.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Software Engineering Series</summary></entry><entry><title>Starterkit Series</title><link href="kujua.github.io/2016/08/01/about-starterkit-series.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starterkit Series" /><published>2016-08-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>kujua.github.io/2016/08/01/about-starterkit-series</id><content type="html" xml:base="kujua.github.io/2016/08/01/about-starterkit-series.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;starterkit-series&quot;&gt;Starterkit Series&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The books in this series are introductions into a well defined software development topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each book has the following features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Short (~100 pages)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intensive discussion of one topic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extensive code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optional goodies like videos or container definitions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start project creator to get a custom starterkit for own projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><summary>Starterkit Series</summary></entry><entry><title>Windows 10 - First Impressions</title><link href="kujua.github.io/2015/09/12/windows-10-first-impressions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Windows 10 - First Impressions" /><published>2015-09-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-09-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>kujua.github.io/2015/09/12/windows-10-first-impressions</id><content type="html" xml:base="kujua.github.io/2015/09/12/windows-10-first-impressions.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Windows 10 finally arrived on my developer machine. Read here about the first impressions with the “RTM” version.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, Microsoft tries to convince us that there are only update versions and no RTM version.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Following are a few impressions I got from working with Windows 10 for a couple of weeks. I am not talking about a beta version, but about the release version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we start I have to emphasize that I am working (and earning money) with development products from Microsoft since the beginning 90s. Not exclusively, but most of this time. In the last 10 years the percentage changed and other operating systems and development environments came into the mix. This does not mean I am a fanboy, it just means that I would like Microsoft to succeed - for my own profit as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a developer also means to be a user of Windows since version 3.0, a journey with all highs and lows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Updates&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my biggest problem: even with the Pro-version it is not possible to schedule system updates for a convenient time. I divide my time between Europe and Africa and in Kenya I am using a satellite internet connection. This connection is in fact metered during the day, but unlimited downloads are possible during the night. There is no way - at least I have not found it - to tell Windows 10 that it should not download updates during certain hours. I can schedule the restart, but by then everything has already happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, don’t forget to uncheck the download option for other Microsoft products - especially Office. Otherwise another 1 GB and more will be downloaded on a monthly basis. Why Office needs so many and big updates is beyond me, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Font Rendering&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some applications’ text renders awfully. Characters are blurry and almost unreadable. For exmple, it happened to me with Enterprise Architect. Menu text, diagram text etc. was so badly rendered that I could not work. Fortunately it is possible to fix this. In the exe-file properties dialog in the tab ‘Compatibility’ it is possible to uncheck ‘DPI Compatibility’ and after a restart of the application everything looked for me as it should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;kujua.github.io/res/disabledpi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Properties Dialog&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not tried it myself, but there seems to be a problem with font rendering on high dpi monitors. A problem that begs belief after this long beta testing phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edge&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft is selling Edge as the new and future proof browser. We all know that some features like extensions are simply missing and it is not clear when they will be added.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The startup time of Edge reminds me of IE: sometimes it takes so long even to open a local page that I can start Chrome (which is not the fastest starter) and display the page I want before Edge renders it. I was thinking that it may have something to do with starting Edge the first time and subsequent starts will be faster, but the startup time is unpredictable and intermittent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started Edge the first time, it asked me to import bookmarks from other browsers. I agreed and the result was very unexpected: All bookmarks were there, but in reversed order with the oldest on top and all the folders in reversed order as well. In Chrome ‘News’ is on the left side of the bookmark bar, in Edge it is in the overflow on the right, because it does not fit into Edge’s bookmark bar. Is it really so difficult to get a feature like this right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cortana&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, I am in different locations with my development laptop and this throws off all applications with location checking completely. My satellite internet connection in Kenya hits the first ground server in different places, in my case most of the time in Greece. This has funny - or not so funny - consequences. For example, my wife has a yahoo email address that she checks from time to time. Yahoo of course believes, that she is sitting in Greece and displays Greek text which we both can’t read. Even deleting all cookies for the site and restarting did not help, the Yahoo website rechecked and all was in Greek again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cortana has a similar problem and displays news from Greece, weather from Athens and so on. Again, I did not find a switch to tell the program not to use the current location, but a defined one. This renders Cortana for me for some aspects more or less useless, because I get recommendations and information for a wrong location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otherwise am not really sold: searching does not really bring back my applications or files, too often Cortana goes to the internet and displays results I don’t need. Probably this is a problem of me not using the program properly, but if it is not obvious then the UX is not as good as it should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Default Settings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in previous Windows versions the default settings for Explorer etc. are geared towards normal users. It is no problem to reset some of the settings, for example to display hidden files, file extensions or empty folders. What I don’t like is the change in setting the explorer views for folders. I like to have the file lists sorted by date with the latest file on top. A quick click on ‘Apply to all folders’ helped in Windows versions pre 10. But now it says ‘Apply this setting to all folders of this type’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;kujua.github.io/res/applytofolders.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Folder Properties&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only can’t I see at one glance the type of the folder except seeing a different folder icon, but I have to click ‘Apply’ several times on different folders. If the settings are not changed again as it happened in previous versions is unknown so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For Developers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The update on my development computer was coming late - I guess because of some applications on it that were not or still are not 100% compatible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of those applications is GenyMotion. This is actually an interesting example of an application that relies on a third party software or API that can’t be controlled and is bitten by it. Some applications rely on APIs that are changed over night or just deprecated, like we all have seen with Twitter, Facebook and other big players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GenyMotion needs VirtualBox to work and somehow there is a problem in the communication. The first complaints about non-compatibility with Windows 10 were raised in GenyMotion fora in April and there are still problems. VirtualBox was updated and I used the latest development version, but Oracle still says that VirtualBox is not yet compatible with Windows 10. This after months of beta testing and now two months after release. I got it to work, but from time to time GenyMotion just crashes. I am not blaming the product, it just shows not to be depending on something one can’t control, as others have found out with applications based on Twitter or Facebook APIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windows 10 brings the promise of universal apps and updated .Net libraries. One hyped feature is not available: the new ASP.NET version. It is a refactoring and rewrite of the current version and introduces new features. What I have seen so far it does not fill me with confidence that we get a lightweight framework. It is still in beta (which is more or less an alpha), though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visual Studio 2015 is RTM since July and I am using it on a regular basis. Overall it feels slower than before. For example, when opening a file I have opened several times before it sometimes stops, displays a window with a ‘loading templates’ message and then after a few seconds it displays the file. Starting VS 2015 also takes a while. VS was not a sprinter before, but now I wait a minute or two to see the start page. Waiting another 30 seconds to be logged in into TFS and then opening a solution with not more than 20 projects takes another 30-60 seconds. Sometimes at startup I see the ‘creating MEF graph’ message, almost always the ‘loading components’ message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VS got better in telling the user what is going on, but there is always a slight delay in displaying or removing indicators for error etc. during editing. Fortunately compiling is working fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opening an application that is taking longer to load reminds me of an unexpected ‘feature’: the operating system (in fact the explorer program) does not display the hourglass anymore. I click on a button in the task bar and nothing happens. The cursor stays in pointer mode and as a user I don’t know if I was successful with my request or not. Photoshop is one of those programs that take time to start some background processes before they display the splash screen. VS at least displays the splash screen immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should mention that the only add-on or extension I use is NCrunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universal apps are the latest Microsoft idea to get Windows 10 on many devices and also to make it easier for developers to create those applications. After a 3GB download all the SDKs and emulators were installed and I loaded one of the sample solutions. There are lots of Universal App samples on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Microsoft/Windows-universal-samples&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; and I randomly tried to compile one. It did not work - more than 700 errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason is that one of the packages - actually the only package: Microsoft.NETCore.UniversalWindowsPlatform - was missing. For another solution I am working on I switched off the automatic loading of NuGet packages during build, so the needed package in the sample was missing. Clicking on the NuGet manager showed that the package is installed, so I uninstalled and tried to re-install. It did not work the first time, after a few times closing the solution and installing the package it worked. And no, the ‘restore packages’ option in the solution menu did not work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually I could compile and start the universal app; trying it on a device will have to wait, because Windows 10 for phones is not yet distributed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verdict&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all will see how Windows 10 will develop in the coming months. At the moment there are some quirks as described above. Apart from GenyMotion there were no crashes with the applications I used. Programs that use graphic cards heavily like Photoshop or games seem to work properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some users have memory problems coming from old drivers, but I have not seen that. Monitoring Task Manager I have the feeling that more memory is used or nor freed, but it never goes beyond a certain limit. In average the operating system uses 2-2.4 GB on a 8 GB machine, so a computer with less memory might run Windows 10, but it will struggle with additional applications. I don’t think anybody wants to run Visual Studio on a 4 GB machine, but it is certainly harder with Windows 10. Switching off certain features like Cortana can help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, all operating systems including OS X and Linux flavors like Ubuntu get very memory hungry and weighted down with non-necessary features, Windows 10 is not different. Privacy is another topic and all systems call ‘home’, more or less and more or less configurable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For developers, Windows 10 should bring new opportunities, but at the moment it does not feel ready. We will see, if the promises will be fulfilled in future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Windows 10 finally arrived on my developer machine. Read here about the first impressions with the “RTM” version.</summary></entry><entry><title>Akka.net Experiences</title><link href="kujua.github.io/2015/07/31/akka-dotnet-experiences.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Akka.net Experiences" /><published>2015-07-31T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-07-31T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>kujua.github.io/2015/07/31/akka-dotnet-experiences</id><content type="html" xml:base="kujua.github.io/2015/07/31/akka-dotnet-experiences.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The actor model is the new cool in the .Net world. The concept as such is more than 40 years old and widely used.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Programming with the actor model is not difficult, but we always have to keep in our minds that everything we do in this model is asynchronous. Usually, web applications in .Net were written in a pure synchronous way: a request comes in, the request is handled on the server, a response is sent back to the client. If the processing takes to long, the connection between the client and the server times out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a simple and effective way to write web applications, although eventually the app will run into scalability problems with either too many concurrent users or backend bottlenecks like database access. Tasks, &lt;em&gt;async&lt;/em&gt;- and &lt;em&gt;wait&lt;/em&gt;- keywords now take care of asynchronous communication in .Net, but especially their contagious nature is putting many developers off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actor model does not solve this problem without work having to be done by the developer, but it gives a conceptual framework for how to ease the problems. The concept is 40 years old and has been implemented in different languages, Erlang - itself 30 years old - is one of the prime examples. The Java and Scala community has Akka and this is implementation now ported to .Net as Akka.net, which has had its 1.0 release not long time ago: &lt;a href=&quot;https://getakka.net&quot;&gt;Akka.net&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Documentation for Akka.net is somehow thin, but it is possible to read the very good Akka documentation either for Java or better Scala and get an idea what the framework is about. There are some examples on Github, but going deeper into development will soon let you run against walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am doing a project with Akka for a company and - bound by an NDA - I can’t say too much about it or show real code, but I can give some notes about my experiences so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes on messaging&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very important to use immutable messages for communication with and between actors. I opt for a simple message structure with a hash or dictionary as the main transport for business domain values. The reason for this is to avoid serialization and deserialization problems and enhance performance. Also, updates can be done without breaking existing actor versions. An actor just takes out from the hash what it needs for processing the data and leaves the rest alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;kujua.github.io/res/actormodel-generic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Actor Messaging&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tricky part is actor-to-actor communication regarding response messages. There are two options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tell is the fire-and-forget option. It sends a message to an actor and processes the next message in its queue.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask is the synchronous option. It sends a message to an actor and waits for the answer, optionally with defining a timeout. &lt;em&gt;Synchronous&lt;/em&gt; is not 100% correct, because the Ask-call can be wrapped in a closure or anonymous function and if it is decorated with the &lt;em&gt;async&lt;/em&gt;-keyword it can be awaited, making the call asynchronous for the system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, the second option is blocking the processing of more messages from the actor’s queue, so it needs to be used with caution. In a project’s code you will probably use more Tell- than Ask-communication to keep the system responsive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes on actor hierarchy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally actors are grouped by the business process they support. In my designs for business apps there always exists a supervisor, which is a normal actor and distributes the work to other actors in the group. The supervisor is the only actor that knows the business process and handles errors and other responses from the other actors in the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;kujua.github.io/res/actormodel-supervisor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Supervisor Hierarchy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also possible to create supervisors for each user of an application and keep the state of this user in the actor. Microsoft’s &lt;em&gt;Halo&lt;/em&gt; implementation used this approach for multiplayer games, although with their own actor model implementation &lt;em&gt;Orleans&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes on remote actors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actor groups can be deployed in containers, which exposes and listens to a TCP port that is unique in the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For calling actors in remote containers, it is necessary to know the address, which is similar to &lt;em&gt;“akka.tcp://server@localhost:8042/user/remotesupervisor”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible to get the supervisor reference from the container, but this requires some global variable magic. The location lookup with a predefined address in the configuration is not as accurate as an actor reference. The reference tells us that there is an existent actor, the location lookup, called &lt;em&gt;ActorSelection&lt;/em&gt;, just gives us an actor address which might have an existing actor behind it or not. Both cases allow valid calls and do not throw an exception if there is no actor to take a message sent to it. Messages without recipient end up in the &lt;em&gt;DeadLetter&lt;/em&gt; queue, by the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking of containers: who does not think of Docker containers? On Windows it is not possible at the moment, but I am sure it will come soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More coming later.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>The actor model is the new cool in the .Net world. The concept as such is more than 40 years old and widely used.</summary></entry><entry><title>The Future of Web Applications</title><link href="kujua.github.io/2015/06/17/future-web-applications.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future of Web Applications" /><published>2015-06-17T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-06-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>kujua.github.io/2015/06/17/future-web-applications</id><content type="html" xml:base="kujua.github.io/2015/06/17/future-web-applications.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have pure web applications a future in view of mobile apps or will they slowly disppear? Let’s investigate.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I talk to fellow developers and mention the possibility that web applications as we see them now will disappear they look at me with big eyes, shake their head, turn around and walk away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note the term &lt;em&gt;web applications&lt;/em&gt;. We are not talking of web sites like a blog that delivers content, but applications with forms, charts, dynamic content from several web services and a user interface that is close to traditional desktop applications. And we are also not talking primarily about native vs web apps on mobile devices, we are talking more about the devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am spending most of the time of the year in Africa in Kenya and there people - who actually can afford it - are using smart phones as main device, especially Android based. Of course, some have laptops, but for various reasons the majority does not want to carry them around. Also, internet access speed is flaky at times, depending on the location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we as an industry developed web applications in the last decade, the emphasis was on features. Often backend developers were forced to &lt;em&gt;design&lt;/em&gt; a user interface for the web which was more practical than usable if usable at all for non-technical users. My own &lt;em&gt;creations&lt;/em&gt; from this time are no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays the emphasis is on the UI with designers and sometimes barely Javascript-speaking novices creating single page applications with the help of more or less powerful frameworks like Angular, Ember and others. Content or data is pulled in from REST services or CMS databases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach is fine for desktop applications with good internet access, but is less viable for mobile devices with high-latency internet connections. The frameworks are doing a better job now to support the fragmentation in the mobile device market regarding screen sizes and screen resolutions, but features like offline usage of apps is not always implementation standard yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The performance and feature discussion about native vs web applications will be resolved eventually, although just now - depending on features demands on the device - native developments are better for many applications. Systems that let developers write their mobile applications in one language and transpile to native code before deployment like Xamarin are helping bridging the gap at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can we transfer web applications written for the desktop one-to-one to a mobile device? Some will say ‘Yes’, others will say ‘No’. I am in the camp of the latter, thinking for example of different approaches to navigation. It is quite possible that in a few years all major mobile platforms may have the same apporach and controls that are not distinguishable from each other. At the moment this is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also do not think that JavaScript is the future of everything. ES6 is moving closer to the object oriented programming paradigm, while many developers are embracing the functional paradigm or at least a hybrid Object Oriented-Functional concept. Not to talk about the &lt;em&gt;isomorphic&lt;/em&gt; approach - a phrase that lets anyone who dug a bit deeper into mathematics shout out in pain. There is a reason why there were many languages invented for server side programming and JavaScript was not one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where are we going?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess we will develop for mobile devices first and only; the desktop browser application will be a side project, but not an afterthought of course. The language used may be any suitable language and the application will be deployed as a native app, where &lt;em&gt;native&lt;/em&gt; can certainly include web view apps once the gaps in performance, looks and native feature access are closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The applications will have strong offline capabilities and will save data to and retrieve data from services on cloud servers, restful or not. Security will be paramount and services will have to be optimized to minimize access time and deal with the latency and changing speeds of on-the-go internet access.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Have pure web applications a future in view of mobile apps or will they slowly disppear? Let’s investigate.</summary></entry><entry><title>Agile Development</title><link href="kujua.github.io/2015/05/20/agile-development.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Agile Development" /><published>2015-05-20T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-05-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>kujua.github.io/2015/05/20/agile-development</id><content type="html" xml:base="kujua.github.io/2015/05/20/agile-development.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;During my career I had many technical interviews. This post is about one aspect that changed over time: development process paradigm.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty years ago nobody was asking about methodologies. It was assumed that the project runs a waterfall process and nothing else was considered, at least not in the enterprise world with Microsoft technology. Around the millenium change I heard more questions about the Unified Process. I remember that I was warned about the question once and the evening before the interview I tried to get more information about it. At that time the internet was not as rich as it is today, so I was lucky to find some information in one of the books I owned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Unified Development Process was created by the same guys who invented UML: Booch, Jacobson and Rumbaugh. The new ideas were iterations - interleaving different phases of the development process - and a clear departure from a pure waterfall approach where one phase must end before the next phase can start. Around 2000 even the US DoD stated that they prefer an iterative approach to a waterfall approach. At the same time Beck’s &lt;em&gt;Extreme Programming&lt;/em&gt; book was published and a little later the &lt;em&gt;Agile Manifesto&lt;/em&gt; was released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years later the project requirements changed and mostly included the question, if the prospective contractor has worked in an agile project. Of course, everybody said yes. And rightly so, because all projects pretended to be agile. They were not!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this pretending from the start without really implementing it is the problem of agile development today. No project manager will say that they are using waterfall, but in fact they use iterations and intertwined phases of the unified process coupled with daily meetings and endlessly updated backlogs. In addition, the definition of the agile process changes as well with different nuances like scrum or kanban being taken into the mix. And XP was in the background as the pure process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most probably we developers are guilty as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was always an aficionado of proper architecture and design, expresses in UML diagrams. Not that I want to update them when the implementation starts in earnest, but at least at the start of a projects they give an overview what is needed: requirements, use cases, high level architecture, perhaps a deployment diagram. In the 90s we called this HLD. This architecturing and design phase was the first to disappear when doing agile. Later &lt;em&gt;Iteration Zero&lt;/em&gt; was invented for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daily meetings are misunderstood most of the time. They should be - in my understanding - a quick update what a developer has been doing yesterday, what they intend to do today and optionally what hinders them if anything. Not more than a few sentences per developer. If such a meeting does not extend to a full blown one-hour meeting, the usual reply to a question of a developer is that this will be talked about outside of the meeting. Many times this outside does not exist after everybody wanders off to their desks, getting headphones on and staying in their own world until the end of the day with a short interruption for lunch. If at all, one does not want to waste half an hour for lunch if paid by the hour, just having a sandwich at the desk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Test Driven Development&lt;/em&gt; is another paradigm that eventually came up in interviews about 10 years ago. The fact is that project managers demand the skills, but once developers are in the project they realize that no time is allocated for writing tests. Stakeholders see it as a waste of time: “First we deliver something, then we can write some tests to verify.” I have to say I am guilty myself of not writing enough tests, especially when using code somebody else had written. I may have worked in the wrong projects, but I can’t remember a single project apart from my own little sidekicks that even tried to do TDD. Perhaps at the start of a green field project, but soon tests were either not written or their quality deteriorated because they were not updated once code changed without changing the test first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pair programming is one of the XP big ideas. I personally like to pair with another developer, one writes tests and the other the code to make the test green; the next day the roles change. Unfortunately this practice is almost never implemented. Many developers are so afraid of showing a weakness that they don’t want to work together with somebody else, especially more junior developers. Once you are an old hand with lots of years of experience it is easier to show how many times you need to search on the internet for sometimes embarrassingly trivial syntax. The more junior developer will be thankful to see that the senior ones don’t know everything. The big difference in knowledge often is just to know where to look. Sadly pair programming is a good, but not frequently used idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the deficiencies in our industry is estimating the time to develop a piece of software. There are too many variables to make estimations accurate: requirements are not complete or not understood, there are no designs for implementation of a feature, developers have their own ideas or code from previous projects, developers don’t have enough knowledge of programming languages or frameworks, managers or stakeholders want to hear certain estimations. This is where Planning Poker comes in. Do not estimate the time, but the complexity of a developing task relative to other known development tasks. The problem is that the base tasks are not defined in a project or different developers have different ideas of the complexity. And what happens if customers want to have a quote before a project starts? You tell them we had a nice planning poker and the team decided it has a complexity of 55 on a Fibonacci scale, but we don’t know yet the time it will take nor the overall costs. If you laugh now or shake your head not believing me then have a look at some of the government projects for example in the health service in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Velocity is the follow-up metrics to the planning poker numbers. Add up the points of each task that is completed after a sprint or iteration and compare those numbers over time. The idea is to see the performance of a team over time, but most probably it won’t change much, because the planning poker becomes a self-fulfilling prophesy. If the velocity numbers go down, the team will increase the complexity per task and assign higher numbers and vice versa. The management practice to try to filter out ‘badly performing’ developers is the logical consequence of a misunderstood number game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another output from the planning poker is the backlog. There is always a manager in the agile team who has two tasks: arrange and attend meetings and update the backlog. It is actually the same as they did a few years ago with MS Project files, spreadsheets or other planning tools. Also, the practice has not changed to print out the planning and now the backlogs on lots of paper, without wanting to know that the moment they print it out it is outdated. And most developers I know - including me - think that the whole thing is a waste of time, which is a mistake. It is the practice to have wrong tasks granularity. Is it too fine, developers feel controlled, otherwise it is just an intent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One big topic in the agile process is refactoring. This means to change the implementation to the better without touching existing functionality. It is a very good concept, although not many teams are doing it deliberately. Often refactoring is a side effect when fixing bugs, but nothing else. Management does not buy in to take a code base, review it and change it. If the code is deployed to production, this won’t happen. Of course, as developers we need to see the business side as well and explain better, why refactoring would be an advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is left of the agile development process? If used pragmatically, it can help. Just don’t get caught up in the discussion pure vs impure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>During my career I had many technical interviews. This post is about one aspect that changed over time: development process paradigm.</summary></entry><entry><title>Container solutions - a trial</title><link href="kujua.github.io/2015/04/19/container-solutions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Container solutions - a trial" /><published>2015-04-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-04-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>kujua.github.io/2015/04/19/container-solutions</id><content type="html" xml:base="kujua.github.io/2015/04/19/container-solutions.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The idea of containers is very compelling. We get rid of heavy virtual machines and just serve lightweight application files.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a training environment I wanted to have containers for database, web server and IDE. As far as I know it is not possible, or at least not easily possible, to run interactive user interfaces in Docker. So my idea was to have Vagrant as host for an IDE container and two Docker-containers for the services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I evaluated this setup on an OS X machine. First I installed boot2docker - this is a wrapper for a Linux virtual machine that actually can load the Docker containers and the runtime, because OS X can’t load containers directly. Boot2docker also exists for Windows, but I have not tried it.
The installation went well. I started the application, which spawns a shell, and after a little waiting I had a Docker prompt and everything was working fine.
Installing Vagrant was eventless as well and I could run a Vagrant box without problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to the first test, running a docker container in Vagrant. I specified to run the hello-world container in a vagrantfile:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Vagrant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;configure&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;vm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;provider&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;docker&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;image&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;hello-world&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;remains_running&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a little bit concerned when Vagrant was downloading boot2docker again, apparently a private version as their /docker version is private and not accessible outside of Vagrant. The hello-world container ran and exited and I tried a few times more. I also confirmed that my Docker installation was still working as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time for a break, the computer went to sleep and when I re-started the machine all hell break loose. First I changed my vagrantfile to run two machines, one docker container, one Vagrant box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-spacing: 0&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Vagrant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;configure&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;vm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;define&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;hellodocker&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;hellodocker&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;hellodocker&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;vm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;provider&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;docker&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;vm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;define&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;db&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;db&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;db&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;vm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;box&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;mitchellh/boot2docker&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The docker machine was never brought up. It told me something about “denied access” and trying to start several times did not change anything. The command &lt;em&gt;vagrant status&lt;/em&gt; was hanging and &lt;em&gt;vagrant suspend&lt;/em&gt; told me that the Docker provider does not support this command, which is probably a bug. I thought, restarting the machine would bring it back to a clean state. But that failed as well as uninstalling Vagrant and installing it again. In between I had to kill the VirtualBox headless process, because I could not install Vagrant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My boot2docker installation did not work anymore as well. It could not bring up Docker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end I uninstalled both Vagrant and boot2docker. Re-installing boot2docker at least brought back Docker on the machine. I am not sure what caused the problems. Was it the double installation? Was it the vagrantfile that brought the system into a faulty state? Is it the boot2docker configuration? Is it the operating system?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What concerns me most is that there was no way to get out of the mess, not even re-starting the machine. Vagrant seems to have some persistent cache that survives all events, good or bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually I tried on a Ubuntu virtual machine. The installation went well without problems and I could run Docker containers with or without Vagrant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to mix them - have one Vagrant box for UI related applications and a few Docker containers for services, databases etc. A story for another day…&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>The idea of containers is very compelling. We get rid of heavy virtual machines and just serve lightweight application files.</summary></entry><entry><title>Technical Debt</title><link href="kujua.github.io/2015/04/10/technical-debt.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technical Debt" /><published>2015-04-10T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-04-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>kujua.github.io/2015/04/10/technical-debt</id><content type="html" xml:base="kujua.github.io/2015/04/10/technical-debt.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The topic of technical debt in software development comes up regularly. I am highlighting my experiences in trying to reduce technical debt.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not going to define technical debt. There are lots of definitions and developers and management always seem to embrace the one that goes well with their specific situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general technical debt describes something not desirable, although it is possible to spin this into a strategy. If a development team decides to have a deliberate debt to meet some goals, most probably a deadline, then this can be considered a strategy. At least one could say so afterward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best projects I have been in is when a development team has trust of managers and on the other side is acknowledging project constraints like deadlines or budget. Such a team will make compromises which will result in technical debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with the deliberate approach is that most of the time there is no planning for reducing this debt. Writing more tests to improve coverage, code reviews, refactoring as such are seen by many managers as unproductive and lost time. That those managers brought the project into problems by nurturing unrealistic expectations by stakeholders is a different problem. More serious is that many project managers themselves don’t understand the need for a reduction of technical debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another cause to come into debt is lack of knowledge in the technical team. I can count the projects of the last 20 years on one hand that had an architecture or design document. Most did not even have requirements written down or only a few of them from a time when the project started. The other extreme was one project with a preparation phase of half a year. In that time requirements were logically checked, development and production environments defined, namespaces discussed, a team structure built and a few prototypes designed - not coded. The astonishing fact was that this project actually bought an architecture framework, so this part was no issue at all from the start. At least the development team could write code without incurring too much debt, because the managers were supporting the idea of testing and refactoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that the development paradigm does not really have a positive or negative impact on technical debt. Waterfall or agile or anything in between all want to deliver the best quality. Where projects fail are impatience and money; the impatience of stakeholders who want to see something and budgets that don’t have enough contingency baked in to cater for unexpected situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The software industry does not really have an answer to the biggest problems I have encountered all my career since the 80s: measuring development time, measuring productivity, reacting to changing requirements or features, explaining the process to non-technical stakeholders, estimating development time and thus budgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this context technical debt is a logical consequence of deficiencies in the development process. For developers, at least for me, it is also a fuzzy term. If technical debt means worse than optimal quality then we have to ask when this debt starts and what is &lt;em&gt;optimal quality&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code I write today can be written better tomorrow when I have more knowledge. Code quality changes over time with advances in computer science, availability of tested libraries or new designs of programming languages. In my opinion technical debt never goes away, because the measuring posts move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have an agile development approach established, even in organizations where one would not expect it. Developers are now more in charge of databases and environments than a decade ago. It would be nice if developers would be trusted  to achieve the best quality as possible and let them design and refactor their code as they see fit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>The topic of technical debt in software development comes up regularly. I am highlighting my experiences in trying to reduce technical debt.</summary></entry></feed>

